<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-02T13:26:10-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wholeview Wellness®</title><subtitle>Wholeview Wellness is a boutique addiction treatment program in Midtown Manhattan.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An Addiction Specialist Shares How to Manage Substance Use Urges During a Pandemic Winter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/an-addiction-specialist-shares-how-to-manage-substance-use-urges-during-a-pandemic-winter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Addiction Specialist Shares How to Manage Substance Use Urges During a Pandemic Winter" /><published>2021-02-24T13:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-24T13:01:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/an-addiction-specialist-shares-how-to-manage-substance-use-urges-during-a-pandemic-winter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/an-addiction-specialist-shares-how-to-manage-substance-use-urges-during-a-pandemic-winter/">&lt;p&gt;To understand more about how the winter (and pandemic) can be so difficult for those who struggle with substance use or are in recovery, here are a few things you should know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is the winter hard in general for those who struggle with substance use?&lt;/strong&gt;
There are a lot of factors that come into play that make winter hard for those who struggle with alcohol and substance use disorders (SUDs). During colder months, we’re less social, spending more time inside and we’re not exposed to the sunlight that our bodies need. This year, the typical effects of the winter months are aggravated by the pandemic. People aren’t getting out and having the positive social contacts they are used to. For the most part, people are staying home. For some that is isolating, and for others who are living in close quarters with family members, this may lead to conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, some people are affected by seasonal affective disorder (SAD). When we are not exposed to enough sunlight, our moods can dip. So, if you have struggled with alcohol or drug use and are also experiencing low mood, add either isolation or conflictual relationships to the mix and you have a recipe for relapse. It’s really not surprising that some people in recovery eventually turn to alcohol or substances to try to lift their mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is the pandemic affecting these typical winter issues?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change to working from home during the pandemic has amplified the challenges that winter months normally pose for people in recovery. Regular routines are disrupted, and people often don’t leave the home for days on end, sometimes finding themselves waking up and working through the entire day.  People can then lose the cadence of self-care that had been folded into their daily routine — the ritual of working out in the morning, having breakfast and taking medications, getting dressed and ready for work, going to a mutual support meeting, having a brisk walk to work, grabbing a coffee, these all dissolve into the monotony of one day sliding into another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can people who struggle with substance use cope with the extra stressors of winter and the pandemic?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a way to get some exercise every day and get your heart rate up. Whether it is doing yoga on YouTube, doing a bootcamp on a workout app, riding a stationary bike, even just doing pushups, squats and sit ups — exercising is critical to reduce cravings and maintaining your mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintain healthy routines and habits, especially when it comes to participating in treatment and recovery support and taking your medications. One thing that is easier now than ever is that most doctors and therapists have virtual appointments. And attending a mutual support group has never been easier as they are all online. You can attend most of your appointments right from your couch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can loved ones support those who struggle with substance use?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to supporting your loved one who struggles with alcohol or a substance use disorder, start by trying to think of fun activities to do together. Maybe it is listening to a podcast or maybe there is a show that you can look forward to watching every week together. You can cook something new together or take a walk after dinner every night or challenge one another to an online word game or a video game. The goal is to fill your lives with activities that are more reinforcing than alcohol or drug use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, offer to be somebody who will listen nonjudgmentally. Let your loved one know that you are there if they ever want to talk, even if they want to talk about wanting to use. It can be hard to hear that your loved one still thinks about using. But this is completely normal and to be expected, and it is important that they have a place to talk it through. Just because they are thinking about using, doesn’t mean that they will relapse, it just means that the thoughts are coming up.  Having someone who calmly talks them through it is invaluable. You may want to be straightforward and say something simple like, “If you have cravings, you can talk to me about it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**What should you do if your loved one slips and uses alcohol or drugs?
**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your loved one slips, the best thing to do is to help them get back on track as soon as possible and don’t beat them up about it. There is a phenomenon called the abstinence violation effect that we want to avoid. The idea is that if they violate their abstinence by using, they feel so ashamed and helpless that they spiral into a place of self-doubt and shame in which they decide to give up entirely on recovery and slide into a full relapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to understand the abstinence violation effect is to think of dieting. Imagine you are on a diet, and you go into the break room at work and there is a birthday party celebration going on. You struggle for a minute but end up eating a big piece of cake. You might feel angry at yourself. You had vowed not to eat sweets, so you say to yourself, “I completely messed up, I’ll never lose weight!” When your colleagues go back to their offices, you say to yourself, “I’ve already blown it, no use even trying anymore.” And you end up eating the rest of that cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you can acknowledge the slip with a mindset of, “OK, I ate one slice, but I can’t let that get me down. Let me get back on track now.” This is the same with SUDs, if you have a lapse, you can use it as a learning opportunity to understand what happened and try to use that knowledge to prevent a slip in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have slipped, this is a time to lean on your resources and your support system to help you as you continue in your recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you most want those who are struggling with substance use to hear right now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not alone. There are a lot of people who are struggling right now. People are feeling anxious, and they are feeling down. If you’ve struggled with SUD in the past and are having thoughts about using, that’s not unusual, but it is a clue that you need to boost your support systems for awhile. Think about what has been helpful in the past. Are you doing those things, or have they fallen by the wayside?  Maybe it’s time to reach out to someone you trust to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treatment really works.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is significant evidence behind therapies and medications that have been developed for SUD. You have choices! There are many ways to address your drinking or drug use. Some people are more comfortable with abstinence and mutual support groups, while others are more comfortable seeking medical and psychological treatment. Unfortunately, there is no cure for substance use disorders. They are chronic medical disorders much like hypertension and diabetes that need ongoing support and medical care. Right now, there is so much stress and anxiety due to the pandemic and these issues are exacerbated by the winter. Treat yourself with compassion if you are struggling and seek assistance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="&quot;alcohol&quot;" /><category term="&quot;psychology&quot;" /><category term="&quot;seasonal affective disorder&quot;" /><category term="&quot;relapse&quot;" /><category term="&quot;drinking&quot;" /><summary type="html">To understand more about how the winter (and pandemic) can be so difficult for those who struggle with substance use or are in recovery, here are a few things you should know.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">6 Ways To Take A Break From Drinking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/americans-are-drinking-more-during-the-pandemic-heres-how-to-cut-back/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="6 Ways To Take A Break From Drinking" /><published>2021-01-15T10:34:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T10:34:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/americans-are-drinking-more-during-the-pandemic-heres-how-to-cut-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/americans-are-drinking-more-during-the-pandemic-heres-how-to-cut-back/">&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic began spreading across the U.S. in March, stores, restaurants and schools closed down. But liquor stores in many parts of the U.S. were deemed essential and stayed open. Alcohol sales have ticked up during the pandemic, so maybe it’s a good time to ask yourself: Are you drinking more than you’d like to be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people, alcohol is a part of everyday life, but taking a break has its benefits.  But with many of us stuck at home and bars either fully closed or with limited hours, we wanted to get some updated advice from the experts. Here’s what they say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6 Ways To Take A Break From Drinking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about why you drink. Kamala Greene Génecé, a psychologist who specializes in addiction, says it’s important to look at the role alcohol plays in your life. “That will allow you to make specific changes based on the information that you gather,” she says. There’s no need for judgment, but R. Lorraine Collins, a psychologist at the University of Buffalo, recommends asking yourself, “Are you keeping alcohol as … a special beverage for limited situations, or are you engaging in alcohol use across the board?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track how much you drink.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services recommends that if you drink, you should do it moderately: up to one drink a day for women or two drinks for men. But Collins says sometimes people can get confused by what constitutes a drink. “For many people … in their minds, a glass equals a drink,” she says. So it’s important to assess not just what alcohol you’re consuming but how you’re consuming it. Is your glass of wine really just 5 ounces (which equates one drink) or is it more? Mixed drinks often contain more than one shot, and craft beers can contain more alcohol than a standard beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you do drink, be mindful.&lt;/strong&gt;
Collins says there are a couple of tricks to curb your alcohol consumption — that way, you won’t suddenly be on your fourth or fifth drink without even realizing it. To slow down consumption, Collins recommends sipping, not guzzling. “Even a beer can be sipped like fine wine,” she says. Additionally, she recommends adding in nonalcoholic beverages between that cocktail or beer and having food available when you drink.
If you or someone you know is struggling with addiction, the SAMHSA National Helpline is open 24/7 at 800-662-HELP (4357). You can get help finding treatment here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reprogram your day.&lt;/strong&gt;
Replace happy hour with a new habit. If you want to take a temporary break from drinking, Génecé recommends starting with a two-week hiatus. She says this will give you a lot of information about your relationship to alcohol: Was it a breeze, or was it really difficult to cut alcohol out of your routine? If the latter is true, she says it’s important to replace drinking with new habits. So, for example, if you like to have a drink after work, try something else at that time, such as going for a walk or watching a show you like. “Substitute other pleasant activities during that very same time for at least two to three weeks so that you can begin to develop a new conditioned response,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connection is key.&lt;/strong&gt; 
Seek out support. Génecé says one of the silver linings of the pandemic is that many of the alcohol support groups such as Alcoholic Anonymous, Smart Recovery and Recovery Dharma have extensive online communities now. For people trying to take a break from drinking, online AA meetings or other similar groups can help you learn more about the help and support available — and meet other people who don’t drink. Even if this more structured assistance isn’t for you, getting support in some form helps — even if it’s just something to distract you from your old routine, such as joining a remote book club or calling an old friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider a break as an opportunity to learn more about yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A break from alcohol can lead to a range of outcomes. As we’ve reported, a 2016 British study of people who participated in a monthlong “Dry January” break, found that 82% said they felt a sense of achievement. “Better sleep” was cited by 62%, and 49% said they lost some weight. Génecé says try to take notice any positive changes in your life without alcohol — maybe you hike farther, have better conversations or get better sleep. Notice if your life feels richer to you. If we’re stuck at home for now, why not give it a try? What do you have to lose?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamala Greene Genece, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="interview" /><category term="drinking" /><category term="alcohol" /><category term="pandemic" /><category term="wine" /><category term="liquor" /><category term="addiction" /><summary type="html">When the pandemic began spreading across the U.S. in March, stores, restaurants and schools closed down. But liquor stores in many parts of the U.S. were deemed essential and stayed open. Alcohol sales have ticked up during the pandemic, so maybe it’s a good time to ask yourself: Are you drinking more than you’d like to be?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advice for People In Recovery During the Holidays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/advice-for-people-in-recovery-during-the-holidays/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice for People In Recovery During the Holidays" /><published>2020-12-21T14:37:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T14:37:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/advice-for-people-in-recovery-during-the-holidays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/advice-for-people-in-recovery-during-the-holidays/">&lt;p&gt;The holidays can present difficult challenges for people in recovery from drug or alcohol use disorder. Even in the best of times, people may experience anxiety and stress related to the holiday season whether due to increased family time, travel fatigue, or unrealistic expectations of holiday happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has not been the best of times. And, of course, the uncertainties surrounding the COVID-19 pandemic have added to the usual litany of holiday stressors. Some individuals in recovery may even opt out of seasonal festivities to avoid relapse triggers that can lead to feelings of loneliness and isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is no one-size-fits-all plan to ease holiday anxiety for those in recovery, below are a few helpful tips that I offer my patients during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember, you are not alone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals can often feel a sense of shame about their addiction. Also, they may be reluctant to share their thoughts and feelings with friends and family over the holidays. This can further increase feelings of isolation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, nearly 21 million Americans struggle with alcohol or substance use issues. So this is not a struggle that you are facing alone. People all over the world are trying to cope with the same challenges you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know your triggers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any situation was designed to trigger a relapse, visiting family and friends in a setting of celebration is potentially at the top of the list. Although the holidays may look different for you this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing family or friends in-person or even virtually may prompt emotional memories, even traumatic ones. This can elicit a desire to use drugs or alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are celebrating the holidays alone this year, loneliness can also be a potential trigger. It is important to mentally prepare yourself by identifying likely triggers that will test your sobriety during the holiday season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop an “emergency plan” before there is an emergency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have written down your triggers, visualize how you would respond when confronted with each triggering situation, such as an emotionally fraught discussion with a family member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to develop an emergency plan in advance, so you are ready to navigate uncomfortable situations that place you at a high risk of relapsing. You don’t want to have to figure it out on the fly. For example, you may want to bookend a therapy session or support group meeting both before and after a social engagement you suspect will be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stick with a friend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identify a sober friend you can check in with over the holidays. It should be someone who can help you with your emergency plan. Your friend can attend socially distant events with you or even check in with you virtually. This can help ensure that you are able to properly assess the situation and leave if any events seem too high of a risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should always have an exit strategy. Your friend can help, or he or she can simply be available to talk during or after a challenging situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ensure you are engaged in your treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past year has caused a lot of uncertainty for everyone. Many individuals in recovery have had to adjust their recovery journey to adapt to this unprecedented time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that you maintain your normal schedule as much as possible. If you usually attend in-person peer support meetings, but no longer have the option to do so, it is important that you take advantage of the many virtual meeting options available right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, it might be important to schedule a meeting before and after holiday celebrations to keep you on track. In addition to meetings, it is important to attend all scheduled therapy and medical visits (whether virtual or in-person).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most comprehensive treatment for addiction combines two approaches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medication to help reduce cravings and prevent relapse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;psychosocial support to help manage the social and emotional aspects of addiction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you currently take medication as part of your treatment regimen, it is important that you stay on track and take your medications as prescribed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on others&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holidays are a time for giving, and great thinkers over the centuries have reminded us that our acts of kindness benefit us as well as those we help.[1] Science has now shown that reward processing [2] in the brain kicks into a higher gear when we perform altruistic acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding an activity that contributes positively to your family, friends, community, or a group that you are passionate about can help you refocus on the meaning of the season. It can also keep you preoccupied and away from potentially triggering situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redefine fun&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes those in recovery look back on their previous days of substance use and find themselves romanticizing the situation. They may only remember the fun while forgetting the challenges and difficulties associated with using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year try redefining what “fun” means to you. Instead of getting together for drinks, perhaps have a cookie bake-off (virtual or in-person), play board games, or host a holiday movie trivia night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HALT! Pay attention to your internal cues
The acronym HALT stands for&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hungry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;angry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lonely&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tired&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are states in which someone in recovery is particularly vulnerable to relapsing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More fundamentally, the concept of HALT is a reminder for you to stop for a minute and think about whether you are truly caring for yourself. Are you getting too little sleep or feeling isolated? Now might be a good time to try some meditation techniques, eat a healthy meal, or call a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are heading into a situation that is high risk, take a minute to do a quick self-check to see if you are hungry, angry, lonely, or tired and decide if you really want to attend. Or if you might want to eat, calm down, or rest before going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exercise, exercise, exercise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise increases the production of endorphins. These are “feel good” chemicals in the brain that reward us when we do the right thing. As I noted before, this is the same reward center that comes under attack with substance use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One study [3] in morphine-addicted rats found that rats who underwent swimming exercises voluntarily reduced their consumption of morphine compared with sedentary rats. Studies [4] in humans [5] have also shown that people who participate in exercise programs reduce their drug use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Final Takeaway on Holiday Challenges in Recovery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year has been a challenging time for everyone, but if you are experiencing difficulties in your recovery, or are just getting started, don’t hesitate to reach out to a healthcare professional to get support. With these tips, people in recovery can set themselves up for success as we head into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santi J. The Secret to Happiness is Helping Others. Time Magazine (undated), https://time.com/collection/guide-to-happiness/4070299/secret-to-happiness/ Accessed 12/18/20.
Filkowski M, Cochran R, Haas B. Altruistic behavior: mapping responses in the brain. 2017 Jun 2. Published in final edited form as: Neurosci Neuroecon. 2016; 5: 65–75.Published online 2016 Nov https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5456281. Accessed 12/18/20.
Gorji H, Hosseini S. Swimming reduces the severity of physical and psychological dependence and voluntary morphine consumption in morphine-dependent rats. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25498794/Accessed 12/17/20
Roessler K. Exercise treatment for drug abuse–a Danish pilot study, Scand J Public Health, 2010 Aug;38(6):664-9, doi: 10.1177/1403494810371249. Epub 2010 Jun 7. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20529968/ Accessed 12/18/20.
Brown R. Abrantes A, Read, J et al. A Pilot Study of Aerobic Exercise as an Adjunctive Treatment for Drug Dependence. Ment Health Phys Act 2010 Jun 1; 3(1): 27–34 https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2889694/ Accessed 12/18/20&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="mental health" /><category term="therapy" /><category term="treatment" /><category term="medication assisted treatment" /><category term="alcohol" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="recovery" /><category term="alcohol use disorder" /><summary type="html">The holidays can present difficult challenges for people in recovery from drug or alcohol use disorder. Even in the best of times, people may experience anxiety and stress related to the holiday season whether due to increased family time, travel fatigue, or unrealistic expectations of holiday happiness.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">5 Things to Know About Vivitrol</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/5-things-to-know-about-vivitrol/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 Things to Know About Vivitrol" /><published>2019-09-15T18:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-15T18:13:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/5-things-to-know-about-vivitrol</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/5-things-to-know-about-vivitrol/">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Sarah Church, a clinical psychologist and executive director of Wholeview Wellness® in New York, shares important details about Vivitrol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 It requires full detoxification to use: “You have to fully taper off opiates to get on Vivitrol. Every day has to be opiate-free for between five to 10 days. If you can’t tolerate that, Vivitrol is not a good option for you. Buprenorphine, (also called Suboxone), can be initiated without going through detoxification. It only requires that you wait until withdrawal symptoms begin, and then it can be given as a rescue medication.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Accessibility is a problem: “Many doctors are not equipped to administer it. Usually, you need to look for an addiction psychiatrist or internist. It’s an injection, and not all physicians are comfortable administering it. You have to seek out someone who is able to administer it. Alkermes has a website that lists providers who offer it in their medical practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 It’s different from Narcan: “Vivitrol is a long-lasting medication. Narcan is short acting. They’re in the same category in that they are both opioid antagonists, they both block opioid receptors, but Narcan only lasts for an hour or two and Vivitrol lasts a month. Narcan is a rescue medication that is frequently used for people who overdose.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 The research is clear: “The FDA approved Vivitrol to treat opioid-dependent patients in 2010. Studies show that people addicted to opioids more than halve their risk of dying due to their use of opioids if they stay on maintenance medication. The most recent study showing that Vivitrol is effective was through the Clinical Trials Network at the National Institute on Drug Abuse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 It’s not just replacing one drug with another: “If you’re taking it as prescribed by a doctor, it’s medicine. It’s part of your recovery. My personal opinion is that people should try to take it for six months to a year. But it really depends on how stable they are in their recovery, what their support network looks like and if they are still having cravings. It’s a decision the patient and their medical providers need to make collaboratively.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="drinking" /><category term="alcohol" /><category term="addiction" /><category term="recovery" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Dr. Sarah Church, a clinical psychologist and executive director of Wholeview Wellness® in New York, shares important details about Vivitrol.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Alcohol Use and the Family: How to Support a Family Member Who is Struggling</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/alcohol-use-and-the-family-how-to-support-a-family-member-who-is-struggling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Alcohol Use and the Family: How to Support a Family Member Who is Struggling" /><published>2019-04-11T11:36:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-11T11:36:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/alcohol-use-and-the-family-how-to-support-a-family-member-who-is-struggling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/alcohol-use-and-the-family-how-to-support-a-family-member-who-is-struggling/">&lt;p&gt;Overcoming an addiction is incredibly challenging on one’s own. To alter negative behavior – and enact lasting, positive change – a strong support system is essential. At the core of that support system? Often, it’s family and loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the families we work with enter treatment with high levels of anxiety and depression – and we even see some people experiencing symptoms of trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are often afraid that their loved one might overdose – or injure themselves or someone else by driving under the influence. They worry that they might have legal challenges, arrests, or other significant negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone you love is struggling with an alcohol use, know that treatment is available and effective – and that your support can help with successful recovery. Certain types of therapy – such as family therapy – can help you emerge with a stronger understanding of this impact and how to move forward from its reverberations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know about how your loved one’s alcohol use impacts you and your family, and what you can do to help your loved one heal – while caring for your own wellbeing, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Seek support: Don’t let shame, stigma, or lack of knowledge prevent you from seeking treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family members often don’t know where to turn and feel that they can’t reach out to family and friends because of the shame and stigma associated with alcohol misuse. As a result, they feel isolated and hopeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know that you are far from alone! It is estimated that more than 20 million Americans have an alcohol or other substance use disorder. Given this number, your loved one – and you, by extension – are hardly alone in this struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to seeking individual therapy, joining a support group can help you connect with others who are managing similar stressors, and reduce possible feelings of isolation that might overwhelm you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Learn about available treatments. Treatment is available – and effective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many families aren’t aware that treatment is very effective. There are proven psychotherapies and medications that can help patients slow down and stop their substance use and move into recovery and family members can play a supportive role in their care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several different treatment approaches for recovery, including – but not limited to – cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), motivational interviewing, and mindfulness practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important messages that we share with families is one of hope and optimism. We want them to know that the research shows that treatment for substance use disorders is just as effective as treatment for other chronic medical disorders like diabetes and hypertension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. For family members in denial or rejecting treatment, try “CRAFT”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For family members who want to help a loved one who is refusing treatment, we use a therapy called Community Reinforcement and Family Training (CRAFT). This treatment approach was designed specifically for people who are concerned about a loved one who is drinking and/or using drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRAFT has two main goals: To support the family members, and to help them guide their loved one into treatment. Overall, it has been found to reduce conflict in the family, and it leads to a healthier and more sustainable life for the people who are caring for someone that is struggling with alcohol or drug use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach utilizes non-confrontational behavioral principles to motivate the person to enter treatment. Using these methods, families can learn to change their interactions with their loved one, which results in changes in their loved one’s behavior. CRAFT provides families with hopeful, positive, and effective alternatives to addressing alcohol and substance problems in their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. To help your loved one through the recovery process, try positive reinforcement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you notice that they did something without using – in essence, “catch them” being good – you want to praise them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, if your wife went to your child’s soccer game without drinking, you want to tell her how happy you were that she was able to go to the game without drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your husband came directly home from work without going to a bar and having a few drinks, you want to tell them how great it was that he came straight home and make sure to tell him how much you like spending time with him when he hasn’t been drinking. You can even make him a nice dinner to really reinforce his coming home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are more likely to repeat behaviors that are reinforced, so by praising them for the things they did right, you are increasing the chances they will repeat the positive non-drug using behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Not sure your loved one has an alcohol problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seek professional consultation to help you decide the appropriate course of action 
For anyone wondering if their alcohol or drug use – or that of their loved ones – is interfering in their life: Don’t wait to come in to talk! Many people wait until there is a crisis or an urgent issue arises, but it’s better to come in early to make changes before things get out of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking with a therapist can help you figure out the best course of action depending on your situation. If your loved one does need treatment, getting help for yourself may prove critical for navigating the stress of helping your loved one recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Families whose loved ones are struggling with alcohol use may feel empowered just knowing that there are many effective treatment options. They can feel optimistic that – with the right professional help – their loved one can make positive, lasting changes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="drinking" /><category term="alcohol" /><category term="addiction" /><category term="recovery" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Overcoming an addiction is incredibly challenging on one’s own. To alter negative behavior – and enact lasting, positive change – a strong support system is essential. At the core of that support system? Often, it’s family and loved ones.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Motivational Interviewing For Alcohol Use Disorder</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/motivational-interviewing-for-alcohol-use-disorder/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motivational Interviewing For Alcohol Use Disorder" /><published>2019-04-08T20:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T20:19:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/motivational-interviewing-for-alcohol-use-disorder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/motivational-interviewing-for-alcohol-use-disorder/">&lt;p&gt;Fear of judgement is a powerful deterrent to treatment for individuals struggling with a substance use disorder of any sort, including alcohol. Some who have already tried to overcome their substance use – whether on their own, in support groups, rehab, or elsewhere – may have encountered frustration, perceived failure, and criticism from others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter motivational interviewing (MI). This highly effective therapy is designed to remove all semblance of judgment from therapy sessions, making room for empathy and self-empowerment instead. The goal of motivational interviewing is to strengthen the client’s inherent motivation to change, and find the resources for change within themselves. This, in turn, sets the stage for healing to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how motivational interviewing for alcohol use disorder works, as well as what to expect in a therapy session, and what to look for in a motivational interviewing therapist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How motivational interviewing for alcohol use disorder works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivational interviewing focuses on developing internal motivation, not skills
Providers use motivational interviewing skills to assist clients in motivating themselves to commit to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest is having clients&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reduce their ambivalence about the behavior they want to/need to change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increase the client’s discrepancy between their behavior and their goals and values.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivational interviewing is a gentle, interventional conversation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, motivational interviewing should feel less like an accusation, and more like a &lt;strong&gt;conversation about change&lt;/strong&gt;. Releasing the pressure that other types of substance use treatments often embrace allows the client to decide for themselves their own reasons for overcoming their struggle with alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because of its nuanced nature, it can take place in one session, or in every session.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivational interviewing is helpful for overcoming relapses, too&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a person relapses, motivational interviewing can be very helpful in resuming the change process. Meta-analysis showed that motivational interviewing had a significant and clinically relevant effect in approximately three out of four studies, with an equal effect on physiological (72%) and psychological (75%) diseases. [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivational interviewing can help those with a substance use disorder who are not prepared for change, or not committed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For individuals who are deeply enmeshed in their alcohol use – and are blocked by all that quitting or overcoming it entails, such as frustration, and anger – motivational interviewing can help them lay the groundwork for healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, for those who are already committed to overcoming their substance use disorder, motivational interviewing might not be as helpful, since its main purpose is to identify deep-rooted motivation for change. However, motivation often fluctuates over time and Motivational Interviewing can help to maintain consistent motivation throughout treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don’t have to “admit” to having a substance use disorder to benefit from motivational interviewing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a person is starting to think about making a change in their drinking habits – even if it is before they have made a decision about change – motivational interviewing can be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through the dynamics of this specific type of conversation that clients can find within themselves the desire, need, reasons, and ability to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Even short-term motivational interviewing can be effective for treating alcohol use disorders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a meta-analysis of motivational interviewing research, where interventions provided brief motivational interviewing (i.e., motivational interviewing for only 15 minutes), 64% of the interventions showed a significant effect.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked how much time it takes to “do” motivational interviewing, Bill Miller – one of the ‘founding fathers’ of motivational interviewing – compared the MI  approach to the enjoyment of  classical music. To paraphrase Dr. Miller, ‘MI is similar to a piece of classical music… having the time to listen to the whole piece will give people the most movement, but even just listening to some of it – the best parts of it –  will be able to move people.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When searching for a motivational interviewing therapist for alcohol use disorder, look for someone who was trained by a “MINT” member.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although different types of providers can be trained in motivational interviewing, there is no official certification in motivational interviewing. That said, the best certification to look for is MINT – the “Motivational Interviewing Network of Trainers.” If someone is a member of MINT, they are skilled in motivational interviewing and have remained active in the motivational interviewing world; also, providers who have been trained by a MINT trainer are believed to have been well trained in motivational interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Br J Gen Pract. 2005 Apr;55(513):305-12. Motivational interviewing: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Rubak, S., Sandbaek, A., Lauritzen, T., &amp;amp; Christensen, B.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Jennifer Smith</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="treatment" /><category term="therapy" /><category term="mental health" /><category term="addiction" /><category term="motivational interviewing" /><category term="alcohol use disorder" /><category term="ambivalence" /><category term="MI" /><category term="psychotherapy" /><summary type="html">Fear of judgement is a powerful deterrent to treatment for individuals struggling with a substance use disorder of any sort, including alcohol. Some who have already tried to overcome their substance use – whether on their own, in support groups, rehab, or elsewhere – may have encountered frustration, perceived failure, and criticism from others.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What parents (and everyone else!) should know about Juuling (Vaping)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-parents-and-everyone-else-should-know-about-juuling-vaping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What parents (and everyone else!) should know about Juuling (Vaping)" /><published>2018-12-26T07:14:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-26T07:14:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/what-parents-and-everyone-else-should-know-about-juuling-vaping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-parents-and-everyone-else-should-know-about-juuling-vaping/">&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably heard a lot about teen vaping and Juuling in the news lately.   While e-cigarettes have been around for more than a decade, usage has risen drastically in teen populations in the last few years. Recent statistics are alarming, According to Monitoring the Future, which conducted an annual study for NIDA (The National Institute on Drug Abuse) in 2017, 19% of 12th graders, 16% of 10th-graders and 8% of 8th graders reported vaping nicotine in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what is JUUL?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JUUL (pronouced like “jewel”) is a private company that is one of the largest players in the e-cigarette market.  They make a vaping device that looks like a flash drive, can be charged in any USB charging device, and comes in flavors like creme brulee, fruit medley and cool cucumber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is JUULing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juuling or vaping is when someone uses an e-cigarette by inhaling and exhaling the vapors produced by the device (e.g., e-cigarette, vape pen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is vaping dangerous?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jury is still out on this question.  While many e-cigarette companies discuss the safety of e-cigs over combustible cigarettes, we really don’t know yet.  Because e-cigs are relatively new to the market, very few research studies have been conducted to determine the long-term effects of vaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we know for sure is that e-cigs contain high levels of nicotine and are therefore addictive.  We also know that people who try smoking at a younger age are more likely to develop dependence on nicotine and to have trouble quitting.  Also, teens who use e-cigs like Juul are much more likely to start smoking cigarettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional concern has arisen because the metal coils in vaping devices release small metal flakes when heated. When inhaled, these metal flakes travel deep into the lungs where they cause inflammation and can result in symptoms resembling asthma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the e-liquid contains many chemicals which often include propylene glycol and glycerol, which when heated, break down to formaldehyde, a known carcinogen. Surprisingly, there is much more formaldehyde in vapor than cigarette smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you remember Joe Camel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Camel was an advertising campaign for Camel cigarettes that ran from 1988-1997.  They wanted kids to notice their brand and it worked.  In 1991 90% of 6-year-old children could match a picture of Joe Camel with a picture of a cigarette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advertising to Teens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, high rates of teens, about 70%, report seeing advertising for e-cigs across multiple channels including, tv, newspaper, magazine ads, internet, and retail.  In 2016 advertising e-cigs directly to teens was banned, but online advertising is not regulated in the same way and often reaches teens who click on ads unknowingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As rates of teen e-cig rise to concerning rates, the US government and the public increased pressure on Juul.  In November 2018 Juul voluntarily agreed to stop selling most of their flavored pods at retail stores and agreed to discontinue social media promotions. However, critics state that young users continue to post on their social media accounts, so Juul no longer needs to do their own advertising because teen users are doing it for them.  Teens end up being exposed to information about vaping on social media regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to tell your kids about vaping?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give them the facts and keep an open dialogue with them about what they are hearing and what their friends are doing.  Make sure they know that vaping involves nicotine, which is addictive. Many teens mistakenly think that the vapor only contains flavoring, they don’t realize that it contains nicotine and other potentially harmful chemicals, so it’s especially important that they are aware of what is in the vaper. Smoking may seem “Cool” even though it’s dangerous, vaping can be perceived the same way especially because of the flavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As kids grow up there are so many things that are competing for their time and attention, it is important to help them navigate the social landscape where they want to be accepted and fit in. Vaping may not seem that dangerous to them, so it’s important that we educate ourselves and our children about the real risk factors involved.  Opening up an honest conversation about vaping is the best way to ensure that teens are informed and can make good decisions. At &lt;a href=&quot;https://wholeview.co/&quot;&gt;Wholeview Wellness®&lt;/a&gt; we provide treatment for people who struggle to stop using nicotine.  If you are interested in learning more about treatment to stop using e-cigarettes, don’t hesitate to call us at 212-204-8430.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="juuling" /><category term="vaping" /><category term="e-cigarettes" /><category term="nicotine" /><summary type="html">You’ve probably heard a lot about teen vaping and Juuling in the news lately. While e-cigarettes have been around for more than a decade, usage has risen drastically in teen populations in the last few years. Recent statistics are alarming, According to Monitoring the Future, which conducted an annual study for NIDA (The National Institute on Drug Abuse) in 2017, 19% of 12th graders, 16% of 10th-graders and 8% of 8th graders reported vaping nicotine in the past year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Opioid Crisis Has Entered the Workforce: What Is an Employer to Do?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-opioid-crisis-has-entered-the-workforce-what-is-an-employer-to-do/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Opioid Crisis Has Entered the Workforce: What Is an Employer to Do?" /><published>2018-10-10T13:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-10T13:56:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/the-opioid-crisis-has-entered-the-workforce-what-is-an-employer-to-do</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-opioid-crisis-has-entered-the-workforce-what-is-an-employer-to-do/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As rates of opioid addiction and substance abuse continue to grow in the United States, the crisis is also beginning to negatively impact employers. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/21/business/economy/opioid-overdose-workplace.html&quot;&gt;New York Times article highlighted startling increases in overdoses&lt;/a&gt; in workplaces throughout the country. The National Safety Council reports that 70 percent of companies acknowledge being impacted by employees affected by prescription drug misuse — a development that drives absenteeism, accidents, injuries and other problematic behavior. In 2016, companies reportedly spent $2.6 billion for treatment of opioid abuse, a figure that doesn’t include additional losses due to performance issues and employee turnover. Dr. Sarah Church, the Founder of Wholeview Wellness®, recently shared ways for employers to address the issues they face.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identifying the Costs of Substance Abuse in the Workplace&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these significant and growing issues in the workforce, employers have been slow to create programs to address the crisis’ challenging issues. Employers’ sluggish response is likely due to a combination of disbelief, inability to identify drug use because of inadequate testing (e.g., not testing for newer synthetic opioids such as fentanyl and oxycodone), and lack of knowledge and training on how to respond effectively. Despite hard evidence including prescription reports and national data, many employers continue to deny having substance use problems within their own companies, somehow believing that the problem is occurring elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employers can identify if this is an issue in their own company by calculating changing costs. The National Safety Council and national nonprofit Shatterproof worked with NORC at the University of Chicago to create a relevant and user-friendly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shatterproof.org/workplace-cost-calculator&quot;&gt;calculator&lt;/a&gt; that determines the cost of substance use in a company. By entering industry (e.g. mining, retail, finance, etc.), location, and the number of employees, the calculator can estimate the costs associated with lost time, turnover, and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many business leaders may be surprised at how expensive it is to disregard this problem and not help people access treatment, since substance misuse by employees is both expensive and unproductive for employers. Providing a clear path to wellness for employees struggling with substance use disorders can be a great investment. Healthcare and other costs can be lowered substantially by developing a culture of openness and wellness while ensuring employees know what their treatment options are from the outset of their employment, which creates an environment where they know they can come forward without fear of retaliation or threat of job loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing a Culture of Assistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is difficult to predict which employees might struggle, it is beneficial to implement these programs company-wide so that everyone has access to services when
they are needed. This also helps develop a culture that all supervisors and employees
share responsibility for keeping each other safe and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So how does an employer get started? Here are a few good steps to take:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start by acknowledging that substance misuse can have a serious impact on the
workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inform employees that you have a drug-free workplace policy and program during
onboarding and periodically afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ensure that everyone in the workplace understands that a drug-free workplace is more likely to be a safe, healthy, and productive environment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Expand drug testing panels to include synthetic opioids including fentanyl and
oxycodone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Train supervisors and employees how to identify the signs and symptoms of substance misuse.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encourage employees to treat and talk about substance use problems as a medical
disorder, not as a justification for termination.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a discussion with your health insurance plan to ensure they offer effective
alternatives to opioids for the treatment of pain (e.g., non-opioid medications, physical therapy, acupuncture, and psychological treatments like cognitive behavioral therapy), that they use stringent opioid prescribing guidelines, and that they support medication assisted treatment (e.g., methadone, Suboxone, and Vivitrol).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Leverage Employee Assistance Programs and relationships with outside providers,
such as treatment providers and healthcare professionals, to help employees return to
work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although actively addressing substance misuse in the workplace may seem daunting at
first, it is a great opportunity for providing both healthcare and other cost savings while also improving the health of employees and their families.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="opioids" /><category term="workplace wellness" /><category term="overdose" /><category term="treatment" /><category term="healthcare savings" /><summary type="html">As rates of opioid addiction and substance abuse continue to grow in the United States, the crisis is also beginning to negatively impact employers. A recent New York Times article highlighted startling increases in overdoses in workplaces throughout the country. The National Safety Council reports that 70 percent of companies acknowledge being impacted by employees affected by prescription drug misuse — a development that drives absenteeism, accidents, injuries and other problematic behavior. In 2016, companies reportedly spent $2.6 billion for treatment of opioid abuse, a figure that doesn’t include additional losses due to performance issues and employee turnover. Dr. Sarah Church, the Founder of Wholeview Wellness®, recently shared ways for employers to address the issues they face.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Demi Lovato, what we know, what we’ve learned, and how she can win her fight</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/demi-lovato-what-we-know-what-weve-learned-and-how-she-can-win-her-fight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demi Lovato, what we know, what we’ve learned, and how she can win her fight" /><published>2018-09-17T07:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-17T07:50:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/demi-lovato-what-we-know-what-weve-learned-and-how-she-can-win-her-fight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/demi-lovato-what-we-know-what-weve-learned-and-how-she-can-win-her-fight/">&lt;p&gt;Countless fans, well-wishers and music lovers all over the world were waiting to learn more and understand what happened to Demi. Was it heroin? How close did she come to death? Will she enter treatment? What really happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demi finally made her first public statement on Instagram following her hospitalization due to her reported overdose. Her heartfelt post honestly acknowledged her ongoing struggle with addiction and thanked her fans for their love and support. She finished with the promise, “I will keep fighting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people ask….why do relapses happen? People also wonder if there is a way to keep people like Demi safe and “protected” as they face this struggle. These are important questions to answer especially for people who are trying to support someone they care about who has relapsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do people continue to relapse?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addiction is complex and the issues that lead people to use drugs are complicated. Often people that struggle with addiction, struggle in other areas of their lives. They are in relationships that are not working, they have jobs that are not fulfilling or that are very stressful, and they may have a history of trauma which haunts them or depression which drags them down. Drug use may be seen as an escape, a way to turn off the noise. Getting high might be their refuge, the way to stop the madness for a while. If they don’t engage in therapy to learn new coping skills and strategies and to deal with the underlying issues that initially drove them to use, the most expensive and exclusive rehab stint will not prevent them from seeking out drugs the next time they are home and are stressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it take to be successful in overcoming opiate addiction?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get this question all the time and the answer is simple. To be successful, patients need ongoing individualized care provided by mental health professionals that is evidence based and that combines both psychotherapy and medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demi wisely mentioned in her post “What I’ve learned is that this illness is not something that disappears or fades with time. It is something I must continue to overcome and I have not done yet.” She is right, addiction is a chronic health disorder and must be treated in an ongoing way, just like hypertension and diabetes. There is no cure for addiction yet, so we have to continue to treat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you prevent people from overdosing when they continue to use opiates?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients like Demi who have had a history of overdose should consider taking one of the three FDA approved medications for opioid use disorder (methadone, buprenorphine or naltrexone) all of which reduce the chance of overdose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people who have been tapered off opioids, the best option is naltrexone (also called Vivitrol). This is a medicine that when given as an injection lasts an entire month. Naltrexone blocks all of the opioid receptors in their body and prevents people from feeling the effect of opioids. No matter how much heroin they shoot or snort or how many painkillers they take, they can’t get high. Think of it as car being parked in a spot when another car is looking to park, the spot is taken, so the second car cannot be parked in that spot. When someone is taking naltrexone and they use heroin, the receptors are taken and the heroin can’t get to the receptors to take effect. This medicine provides a safety net that can give patients a chance to engage in therapy and it protects them from overdose if they relapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients should also have a narcan overdose prevention kit on hand in case they overdose. Narcan is a medication that can be administered by lay people who have been trained to provide it. In case of overdose, it can be given intranasally, just like Afrin for a stuffy nose. Anyone with a history of opioid misuse and anyone who cares about someone who has this history should keep a kit on hand, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hope for the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demi will certainly not be the last person or celebrity to struggle with addiction and to overdose. Astonishingly, more than 60,000 people died from overdoses in the US in 2016. The good news that everyone needs to know, is that effective treatment is available, and the first step starts with a phone call.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="therapy" /><category term="demi lovato" /><category term="opioids" /><category term="heroin" /><summary type="html">Countless fans, well-wishers and music lovers all over the world were waiting to learn more and understand what happened to Demi. Was it heroin? How close did she come to death? Will she enter treatment? What really happened?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sometimes I wonder if I’m drinking too much…Five questions to ask yourself.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/sometimes-i-wonder-if-im-drinking-too-much-dot-dot-dot-five-questions-to-ask-yourself/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sometimes I wonder if I’m drinking too much…Five questions to ask yourself." /><published>2018-09-12T17:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-12T17:48:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/sometimes-i-wonder-if-im-drinking-too-much-dot-dot-dot-five-questions-to-ask-yourself</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/sometimes-i-wonder-if-im-drinking-too-much-dot-dot-dot-five-questions-to-ask-yourself/">&lt;p&gt;Many people drink socially with friends and so do you. You might pour a glass of wine at the end of a long day, meet a friend for a drink after work, or have a glass of rosé during a summer lunch while on vacation. But, what if you a have a few more drinks than than that? You might be wondering if your drinking is having a negative effect on your life. If these thoughts have crossed your mind, ask yourself these five questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When I drink, do I often find that I end up drinking more than I meant to? For example, do I often decide to have one glass of wine, but end up having three or four?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have there been times that I thought I ought to quit, but then I just didn’t end up doing it? In other words, do I wake up in the morning and think I should take some time off from drinking, only to give in when Friday evening rolls around?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do I experience trouble sleeping, anxiety, restlessness, nausea or sweating the morning after drinking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have any of my friends or family members talked to me about my drinking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe I’m doing ok at work, with my family, or in school, but when I really think about it, is it possible that my drinking is keeping me from reaching my full potential?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you answered any “Yes” to any of these questions, there is a possibility that your drinking may be having a negative impact on your social relationships, your work performance and even your health. It’s scary to think that your drinking might be causing issues in your life, but you might want to reach out and talk to your doctor, a friend or someone you trust. The good news is there are many effective techniques that have been proven to help people who are drinking more than they want to. These include staying within low risk drinking limits and spacing out your drinks. You don’t have to wait to “hit bottom” or for a crisis before deciding to make a change. It’s better to make changes early, so that you can prevent things from getting worse. Making a decision to cut down or quit can be hard, so don’t do it alone! Talk it through with someone who supports you or reach out for help.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Church, Ph.D.</name></author><category term="insights" /><category term="blog" /><category term="drinking" /><category term="alcohol" /><category term="addiction" /><category term="recovery" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Many people drink socially with friends and so do you. You might pour a glass of wine at the end of a long day, meet a friend for a drink after work, or have a glass of rosé during a summer lunch while on vacation. But, what if you a have a few more drinks than than that? You might be wondering if your drinking is having a negative effect on your life. If these thoughts have crossed your mind, ask yourself these five questions:</summary></entry></feed>